Guide to the Friends of the Libraries records, 1970-2002 RG0104
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Friends of the Libraries records
1970-2002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
RG0104
4.6 Linear Feet
Materials in this collection include publications, photographs, correspondence, meeting minutes, certificates, and brochures. They range in date from 1970 to 2002.
Restrictions on Access
Series 1 has a 25 years from date of creation restriction.
Acquisition Information
Materials were transferred to the University Archives by the Friends of the Libraries.
Historical or Biographical Note
The George Washington University's Melvin Gelman Library opened in 1973. Before the Gelman Library (which received its current name in 1980), the University Library was located in Lisner Hall, formerly Lisner Library. When the University moved to Foggy Bottom in 1912 from its location on 15th and H Streets, N.W., the first library was located in the original Lisner Hall, the former St. Rose's School for Orphaned Girls, between 20th and 21st Streets on G Street. Other libraries include the Virginia Campus Library (established n 1990), and the Mount Vernon Campus Eckles Library (under GW control since 1997). Together, these three libraries form the Gelman Library System (GLS).
The Jacob Burns Law Library opened in 1967, before that it was housed in the adjacent Stockton Hall on 20th and H Streets, N.W. The Paul Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library opened in 1973, before that it was housed in the old Medical School building on 13th and H Streets, N.W.
In 1972 The Friends of the Libraries was organized. It's original object was "to assist the libraries in carrying out their role more effectively through strengthening their collections and promoting activities to make resources and services of the libraries more widely known. Specifically, we hope the Friends will provide and help attract special collections and resources that support the University's instructional and research programs; sponsor special projects and activities; provide for others a better understanding of the University libraries and their role in our own academic setting; provide and attract new financial support to enrich the book collections of the libraries; and serve as a medium through which our friends may advance their own intellectual pursuits and share their enthusiasm for books and reading."
Membership is open to anybody wishing to contribute, and is overseen by Assistant University Librarian for Administration, Development, and Personnel. Currently there are eight levels: GW student, GW staff, Associate, Supporter, Sponsor, Patron, Benefactor, and Librarian's Circle. Dues can be directed to the Gelman Library, Burns Law Library, Himmelfarb Medical library, Mt. Vernon Campus Library, or Virginia Campus Library. The Friends group is run by a board of directors and executive committee.
The Friends sponsor an annual dinner that features a prominent guest speaker, and supports exhibits, receptions and other special events (such as the Student Collectors Book Contest). The group has also made financial contributions by occasionally purchasing books and equipment of the libraries.
The Friends have also published a number of special "keepsake" volumes over the years, beginning in 1972, such as a facsimile of the opening address given to open the college in 1822 and a booklet commemorating the donation of the one millionth volume to the Gelman library in 1984.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include publications, photographs, correspondence, meeting minutes, certificates, and brochures. They range in date from 1970 to 2002, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Friends of the Libraries.
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: Board members and publications; Certificate; Photographs; and Organization files.
Paul Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library; Libraries -- Special collections; Lisner Library; Jacob Burns Law Library; Melvin Gelman Library; Lisner Hall; Libraries; Library Administration; Research; Finance; Instruction; Washington (D.C.); Photographs; Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); George Washington University; George Washington University. Friends of the Libraries; George Washington University. Library
- Board members and publications, 1972-1989; RG0104 Series 1; 3 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of materials related to Friends of the Libraries board members, the One Millionth volume, annual dinners, student collectors contest, publications (A Woman in the Case, Classical Education, William Staughton address, exhibit brochures (Titian Ramsay Peale, Kelmscott). The materials range in date from 1972-1989, and were transferred to University Archives in 1993.
  Formerly ACC#187
  This series has a paper container list in the reading room, please ask staff for assistance.
- Certificate, 1981; RG0104 Series 2; 1 Linear foot (Flat box 1)
  This series consists of a certificate for Ethel Davis Bloedorn, making her an honorary member of the Friends of the Library. It dates from 1981, and was transferred to University Archives in 1987.
  Formerly ACC#500
  This series has a container list in electronic form, please ask staff for assistance.
- Photographs, 1988; RG0104 Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series consists of photos and contact prints of events, including preservation of materials demonstration in Special Collections department. The materials date from 1988, and were transferred to University Archives in 1995.
  Formerly ACC#475
- Organization files, 1970-2002; RG0104 Series 4; 1 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2)
  This series includes by-laws, brochures, library newsletters, invitations, stationary, annual meeting programs, speeches, correspondence, bibliographies, flyers, questionnaires, agendas, minutes, officer lists, membership lists, nomination lists, obituary, statistics, renewal notices, applications, donation forms, exhibition brochure, publications, copyright registration form, and reports. They range in date from 1970 to 2002. The items cover book review forums, fundraising, committee questionnaire, committee appointments, membership requests, projects, Friends of the Libraries Executive Board of Directors, new building fundraising, Jacob Burns Library, Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library, Gelman Library, Peter Charles L'Enfant, Titan Ramsay Peale, "A Woman in the Case: the Suppressed commencement Address of 1887," treasure's reports, and exhibit labels.
  Formerly vertical files
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries, 01/1972-05/06/1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries--Annual Meetings, 1973-1985, 04/07/1973-05/16/1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries--Annual Meetings, 1986-2002, 05/08/1986-04/17/2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries--Book Reviews Forum, 1974-03/07/1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries--Committees, 01/25/1978-09/1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries--Correspondence, 01/19/1972-04/30/1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries--Executive Board, 11/30/1972-06/19/1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries - Meeting Minutes, 1973-1995, 12/01/1972-03/09/1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries--Membership Committee, 04/13/1972-09/24/1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries--Officers and Membership, 04/13/1972-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries--Publications - Keepsake, 1972, 01/1972-10/01/1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries - Publications - Keepsakes, 06/01/1974-2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries--Special Events Committee, 05/18/1970-02/04/1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Libraries--Friends of the Libraries--Student Book Collectors Contest, 1974-04/15/1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Libraries - Friends of the Libraries --Treasurer's Reports, 11/13/1972-09/08/1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)